Guide to the Sheila Heti Riot Grrrl Collection 1994-1997 MSS.366
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sheila Heti Riot Grrrl Collection
1994-1997
Fales Library and Special Collections
Heti, Sheila, 1976-
MSS.366
2.5 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes
Sheila Heti is a Canadian writer and author of the novels Ticknor and How Should a Person Be? and the story collection The Middle Stories. While Heti was still a teenager, she was asked by Random House to compile an anthology of writing by young women. The Sheila Heti Riot Grrrl Collection represents the zines, poetry and artwork that she solicited for the book, as well as the letters she received from the young women who submitted their work. It covers the years 1994-1997. Random House later decided not to publish the book.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series I: Anthology Submissions
Series II: Administrative Files
Within each series, materials are arranged alphabetically by author's last name or, when no author is available, item title. Loose materials with no discernible author or related submissions are described as miscellaneous submissions.
Biographical Note
Sheila Heti is a writer who was born into a Jewish-Hungarian family in 1976 and grew up in Toronto, Canada. Heti first discovered feminism and the Riot Grrrl movement when she was around 15 or 16 through reading Sassy magazine, Naomi Wolf's The Beauty Myth, and Lynn Crosbie's The Girl Wants To. At a lecture by Wolf in Toronto, Heti spoke during the Q+A about how her own zines ("Iron Maiden"), which she had been putting up around the school, had been torn down by school authorities. She gave an envelope of the zines to Wolf after the talk. Several weeks later, Heti received a letter from Wolf's publicist at Random House, Susan Roxborough, suggesting that they meet to discuss a possible anthology of writing by young women. Heti began soliciting material from all across North America, writing to English teachers at schools and putting out the word through the zine network by exchanging her new zine ("Brillantine") for the zines she received. After about a year and a half of work, she handed in a first draft of the book. It was rejected because the material was too controversial.
Heti studied playwriting at the National Theatre School in Montreal before attending the University of Toronto to study art history and philosophy. In 2001, she created the Trampoline Hall lecture series (hosted by Misha Glouberman). Heti has published five books, including the novels Ticknor and How Should a Person Be? and the story collection The Middle Stories. Her books have been translated into German, French, Spanish, Dutch, Italian and Serbian. Her writing has appeared in The New York Times, The Guardian, The London Review of Books, n+1, McSweeney's, Bookforum, and other places.
Scope and Content
The Sheila Heti Riot Grrrl Collection comprises correspondence and submissions relating to Heti's unpublished anthology of young women's writing, originally commissioned by Random House Canada.
Series I: Anthology Submissions contains submissions mailed to Heti for inclusion in her anthology; these submissions include zines as well as original artwork and poetry, often in addition to correspondence from the authors.
Series II: Administrative Files contains material relating to the publication of the anthology, including Heti's contract with Random House, correspondence regarding the selection of a cover image, and the letter informing participants of the anthology's cancellation. Series II also contains material relating to "Reluctant Hero," one of Heti's zines that features many of the same participants as the anthology.
Provenance
The Sheila Heti Riot Grrrl Collection was donated to NYU's Fales Library and Special Collections by Sheila Heti in 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Riot grrrl movement.; Teenage girls.; Poetry.; Drawings; Correspondence.; Zines; Anthologies|x Editing.; Feminism; Heti, Sheila, 1976-; Random House (Firm)
- Series I: Anthology Submissions
  Scope and Content
  Series I: Anthology Submissions contains submissions mailed to Heti for inclusion in her anthology; these submissions include zines as well as original artwork and poetry, often in addition to correspondence from the authors.
  - Acker, Lori Maleea, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adleman, Alison, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Andrea "Residential Garbage" #2-3; "A Girl" #1-3; "Song for a Rockstar", undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anne "Loud As Hell" #2-6, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aron, Nina "Charm School" #5, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Avery, Felicity, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Azoulay, Karen, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Barnett-Dyer, Sophie, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bennett, Courtney, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bikceem, Ramdasha "Gunk" #4, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bordeaux, Ariel "Deep Girl" #4, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Burnstein, Anna-Lise, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Burt, Mary, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Capo, Venessa, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Castleman, Amanda, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Catching, Rebecca, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cengel, Katya, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chan, Kristy "Wild Honey" #9-10, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Christie, Rachel E., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Courtney, Meighlin "Esteria", 1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Crane, Robin "Sweetheart" #8, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Dainow, Susannah, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Daley, Sarah Joie, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Dame Darcy", 1995 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Dart, Rebecca, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Davis, Jaina A. "Flatter" #5, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dean, Hilary, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Diaz, Karla, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Doyle, Chantale Elena "Misery and Vomit", undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Druffner, Kristen, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Emmenegger, Nicole "Beri-Beri" #1-2 "Busy Bea's Bush" #3, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Faith, Emily, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fatila, Rita "Ugly" #11 "Pure Tuna Fish" #1, 5 "The Sleeping Pill" #1-2, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fierro, Julia, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Flood, Margaret Theresa, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Forbes, Latham, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Garber, Jodi, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Goodman, Sarah, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gretchen "Good Faerie" #12, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hamilton, Sarah, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Harris, Megan, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Harvey, Roseanne, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Hebden, Lisa, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Heinowitz, Rebecca Cole, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hill, Christy, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Horng, Menghsin Cindy "Sidetracked" #1-3, 5-8 "Qiviut" #2, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Hui, Emily, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ishiguro, Rachel, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Jasper Place Composite High School, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Julie "Hell Kitty" #6, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Jurisz, Rebecca "Vilde Chaya" Winter 1995 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Kaysha, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Kelly, Trish "The Make Out Club" #4-5, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Kyra "Died Laughing" #2, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Lake, Meghan "Pout" #6-7, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lambert, Andrea "Bedtime Stories For Trivial Teens" #3-4, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Landry, Stephanie "Modest No More" #1-2, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Larned, Emily K. "Muffin Bones" #10, 15, 1995-1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Lavender, Heart, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Levine, Shira ("She-Ra") "Noisy Jewelry" #1-2, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Luellen, Michelle "Design #816" #7-8, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Lynn, Heather "Pacifier" 2 issues unnumbered "Hands Off" #3, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Manvel, Sarah "Edna's Edibles" #6, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Martin, Lauren "Boredom Sucks" #7-9 "You Might As Well Live" #1, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Mehta, Nishi, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Meyer, Hazel, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Moss, Ceci "Suburbia" #1-6, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Mulholland, Sharon "Some Dumb Girl", 1995 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Neill, Courtney, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - [O'Conerr], [Elane], undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Penny, Marie "Rabbit Hole" "Pearl" #1 "Persephone" #3, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Philpot, Allison, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Poster, Zoe "Pixxiebitch" #5, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Precosky, Krista "What's Life?" #1-2, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "Queen Itchie" "Everything I Touch Turns to Shit & Garbage" #1-2, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Quinlan, Erin "Ritalin" #8, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Robbins, Katharine, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Rodd, Megan, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Rogal, Aren "My Straight-Faced Twin" #2, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Seymour, Ellesen, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Shearn, Amy, 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Sinclair, Leslie, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Snider, Lisa, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Sorensen, Jennifer, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Stehr, Sonia Leonie, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Stone, Emily, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Sturino, Idella, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Terk, Hilary "Weetzie Bat: The Zine" #1-3, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Urbanski, Debbie, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Varner, Christina, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Welch, Jenny, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Witknee "Alien" #6, 8 "Spinsterwitch" #4 "Slumber Party Games", 1996 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Wubbenhorst, Audrey "Rampage" #2-5, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Yun, Blenda, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Series II: Administrative Files
  Series II: Administrative Files contains material relating to the publication of the anthology, including Heti's contract with Random House, correspondence regarding the selection of a cover image, and the letter informing participants of the anthology's cancellation. Series II also contains material relating to "Reluctant Hero," one of Heti's zines that features many of the same participants as the anthology.
  - Anthology - Cancellation Letter, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Anthology - Cover Photo and Related Correspondence, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Anthology - Draft Correspondence, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Anthology - Miscellaneous Submissions, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Anthology - Random House Contract, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Reluctant Hero" - Author Bios, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Reluctant Hero" - Correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Reluctant Hero" - Draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "Reluctant Hero" - Miscellaneous Submissions, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)